Okay, בוקר טוב boker tov everybody, we today's דף daf is יט,
Yud Tes, and it is the thirty-second day of the עומר, Omer,
and we pick up on the top of יט Yud Tes about
six lines from the top with the two dots, תנן התם, tnan
hasam, and we are dealing with the issue about the כהנים Kohanim
wearing of the בגדים. begadim. חוץ מבגדים chutz mebegadim lacking the right
בגדים begadim makes the עבודה avoda פסול, pasul, invalid, and the גמרא
Gemara had like a whole fascinating question, it started getting into the
issue right about about how the not the question necessarily about פסול,
psul, well it could be I guess, but also the question about
how the בגדים begadim have to fit, let's say they're too long,
let's say they're too short, let's say they're the right size but
they're being held up by the belt so they don't get to
the, you know, to the bottoms of, you know, they don't reach
the feet, or let's say they're too long but they're being held
up so they're the right size, you know, sounds like what I
do sometimes if my suits don't fit or whatever, my pants don't
fit. Anyway, so there's all those fascinating questions about right whether that
about about what counts as sort of a בגד beged that it
is כשר kasher for a כהן Kohen and then we got into
the whole question the whole point that it was made out of
linen and, you know, three strands which are twisted and the whole
sort of issue about that. Okay, and now we continue and like
where exactly, you know, you put the belt, you don't put it
under the underarms, etc. Okay, so within that, now let's continue five
lines from the top or six lines from the top, תנן התם,
tnan hasam, top of יט עמוד א, Yud Tes Amud Alef, we
taught over there. כהן
שלקה באצבעו. Kohen she'laka be'etzba'o. Now this is a שבת Shabbos הלכה,
halacha, a כהן Kohen banged his like got a scratch on his
finger, he's bleeding, and you know, you don't want to go ahead
and do the עבודה avoda when you're bleeding all over the place,
not like it's פסול pasul but it's like disgusting. Okay, anyway, so
כורך עליה גמי. koreich aleha gemi. So it's שבת, Shabbos, so you
can tie a certain like a little band around it to stop
the bleeding, essentially an ad hoc band-aid, you know, they only started
making like these pre-packaged band-aids I think was that after the Civil
War, after World War I or something like that, I think it
was after the Civil War. Anyway, right, so you do some bandage
or whatever, במקדש אבל לא במדינה, bamikdash aval lo bamedina, you can
do it in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash but not outside, because
it's a שבת Shabbos issue, and the issue is not like knotting
or whatever you however you get it around it, it's not some
type of a knot or permanent or whatever, you maybe use a
band or an elastic, but I don't know if they had elastic
then. Anyway, but the problem is is that it's a type of
a healing and you're not supposed to do רפואה refuah on שבת,
Shabbos, you know, and when you keep a wound covered you're not
only, you know, preventing yourself from bleeding all over the place, you
know, you're helping the healing process, preventing infection and so on. Okay,
so therefore you are allowed to do it. It's an interesting question,
like nowadays nobody hesitates putting on a bandage on שבת, Shabbos, so
that's an interesting question we can talk discuss it when we talk
about הלכות שבת. hilchos Shabbos. But anyway, here it's considered a type
of a רפואה, refuah, but they don't these prohibitions don't apply in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אין שבות במקדש, ein shvus bamikdash, right,
there's a general waiver for like rabbinic restrictions on שבת Shabbos in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. I mean, there you are, it's שבת,
Shabbos, you're slaughtering these animals. Okay, now that's allowed because for for
קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, you know, you don't you're not bringing regular
קרבנות, korbanos, but but there's once anyway, so you have all already
that sort of license. And in general we want to give greater,
it's a little bit ironic, right, here it is the holiest place
in the holiest time, the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash on שבת, Shabbos,
you know, and we're going to give more license, but to some
degree that's necessary and it's also a function of the fact that
we assume that כהנים Kohanim are going to be careful.
Isn't it a חציצה chatzitza though, having that?
That's exactly why we're bringing it in, but the beginning of the
conversation is a שבת Shabbos one. So we're not concerned about the
rabbinic issue in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash but we are outside
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. במקדש אבל לא במדינה. bamikdash aval lo
bamedina. ואם להוציא ממנו דם, ve'im lehotzi mimenu dam, but if as
you're wrapping it you're trying to like squeeze out some blood, okay,
then כאן וכאן אסור, kan vekan assur, that's forbidden either places because
that's making a wound, that's an איסור issur about חבלה chavala and
so on. Fine, that's the teaching about שבת. Shabbos. Now we're going
to talk about the בגדים begadim issue.
ואם חבלה chavala problem on שבת, Shabbos, you can't make a wound
in general, isn't that like a general thing?
No,
דרך רפואה derech refuah you can't. אמר רב יהודה. amar Rav Yehuda.
So now we're going to that's about the שבת Shabbos issue. Now
we're going to talk about the בגדים begadim issue. אמר רב יהודה
בריה דרב חייא, amar Rav Yehuda brei deRav Chiya, לא שנו אלא
גמי. lo shanu ela gemi. That's only if it's a light type
of like a piece of cloth.
אבל צלצול aval tziltzul I lost my place. אלא גמי אבל צלצול
קטן הוי יתר בגדים. ela gemi aval tziltzul katan havei yeter begadim.
But if it's like some like a little type of a bracelet
or something, you know, some type of a thing that is in
itself decorative or garment or whatever, I don't know who wears bracelets
on their finger, or whatever it would be, but I don't know,
my I said, you know, who knows, maybe it's looks like a
ring or something like that. Anyway, if it's something that's more garment-like,
then it's forbidden because then you're wearing an extra garment. So he
says you can't wear anything on your body that would be defined
as an extra garment, even though this thing here its primary function
is to prevent the bleeding and רפואה, refuah, but if essentially it
is also a בגד, beged, you can't wear it. That's wearing יתר
בגדים. yeter begadim. And that invalidates, you can only wear the exact
בגדים begadim that a כהן Kohen is allowed to wear, which of
course raises the questions of besides that you wouldn't let's say for
example be able to wear a watch, would you be able to
wear where, you know, and a ring for us to wear wedding
rings, and would you be able to wear glasses? Right? Why not?
I mean, you know, this is definitely a type of a garment,
the proof being that on שבת Shabbos without an עירוב, eruv, no,
on שבת Shabbos without an עירוב, eruv, people wear glasses. I mean,
okay, if you're a בריסקער Brisker you don't, because, you know, the
בריסקערס Briskers will say, well, that's not a garment, it's just an
aid for seeing that you carry on your face. Okay, but most
of us, since there's, you know, the, I'm sure the
multi-hundred-million-dollar or billion-dollar industry of selling cheapo, you know, one-dollar frames for
a hundred dollars because it's supposed to be a fashion statement, you
know, whatever, so people treat glasses as a type of a, as,
you know, as a נוי noy and as a garment, and so
on. So anyway, so according to this, it would seem you couldn't
do it. They didn't have glasses in the time, eye glasses in
the time of the גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, so, well, let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes with this. Well, the answer about glasses is
yes, or else you wouldn't be able to wear it on שבת.
Shabbos. Okay, like I'm not allowed, anyway, but we're going to go
on for that. Okay, and so that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says. I'm sorry, that's what רבי יהודה בריה דרבי חייא Rebbi Yehuda
brei de-Rebbi Chiya says, לא שנו אלא אגמי, lo shanu ella agami,
אבל צלצול קטן הוי יתור בגדים, aval tziltzul katan havei yitur begadim,
it's an extra garment. רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says, לא אמרו יתור בגדים אלא במקום בגדים. lo amru yitur begadim
ella bemakom begadim. No, no, no, extra garment is only a problem
where the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna are supposed to be. That part
of your body can only have the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna on
it. אבל שלא במקום בגדים, aval shelo bemakom begadim, in a place
where the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna are not supposed to be, like,
you know, for, I, on your finger, on your face, and so
on. So then, wait a minute, אבל שלא במקום לא הוי יתור,
aval shelo bemakom lo havei yitur, it is not considered an additional
garment. Yes, what was your question? Earrings, that would be another good
example. A צלצול tziltzul is an earring?
No, but just it makes, oh, it makes that sound.
Yeah, an earring would be another good example. Nose rings, no nose
rings for the כהנים. Kohanim. Okay, that would be a good question.
Can a כהן kohen doing the עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash be wearing a nose ring? It's a מחלוקת machlokes אמוראי.
Amora'ei. Yes. Okay, so, אבל שלא לא הוי יתור בגדים. aval shelo
lo havei yitur begadim. ותיפוק ליה, U-teipuk lei, says the גמרא, Gemara,
משום חציצה. mishum chatzitza.
So, one minute, says the גמרא, Gemara, according to the one that
says it's not good because it's an extra garment, why do you
have to say an extra garment, I'm sorry, yeah, why do you
have to say an extra garment? Why don't you say that it's
a problem because it's getting
between, you know, your hand and the עבודה? avoda? We're going to
learn it says ולקח הכהן, ve-lakach ha-kohen, שתהא לקיחה בעיצומו של כהן.
she-tei lekicha be-itzumo shel kohen.
So if I basically am, whatever I'm doing, I'm doing a שחיטה,
shechting, I'm carrying the bowl that has the blood, I'm sprinkling the
blood, it has to directly touch my skin. Okay, it has to
be בעיצומו, be-itzumo, with the essence of the כהן kohen himself. Anything
I do, the עבודה, avoda, I have to directly touch the bowl
or the blood or the knife or whatever it is, I have
to directly touch it with my skin. So if there's a bandage
on, why isn't that bandage a problem of a חציצה? chatzitza? Okay,
and that would be an issue, you know, that would be an
issue, for example, even if it wasn't a צלצול, tziltzul, even if
it was a גמי gami and so on. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ותיפוק ליה, u-teipuk lei, or if it is a צלצול, tziltzul,
why are you saying because it's יתור בגדים? yitur begadim? Say it's
a problem because of חציצה. chatzitza. So the גמרא Gemara says, ותיפוק
ליה משום חציצה, u-teipuk lei mishum chatzitza, so the גמרא Gemara says,
בשמאלו. bismolo. No, you got your cut finger is your left hand
and you're doing the עבודה avoda with the right hand. Can you
wear a ring then according to, if it's not a problem of
יתור בגדים? yitur begadim? There's two problems now: חציצה chatzitza and יתור
בגדים. yitur begadim. So this answer gets out of the חציצה chatzitza
problem. Okay, let's finish this. אינמי inami שלא במקום עבודה. shelo bemakom
avoda. It's a part of your hand that you don't do the
עבודה avoda with. רש"י Rashi says it's on the back of your
hand, it's not the front of your hand, so it's only the
palm of your hand that's going to, let's say, hold the bowl
or something like that. So now what we have is we have
two problems. A: there can't be anything between your skin and the
thing you're doing the עבודה, avoda, the knife, the bowl, the blood
and so on. So that just means that you have to get
rid
of any sort of חציצה chatzitza in those areas, those parts of
your body. But even when we're not dealing with that חציצה chatzitza
problem, is wearing a, you know, nose ring, eye glasses, a bandage
on the back of your hand which is not a חציצה, chatzitza,
is that a יתור בגדים yitur begadim type of an issue if
the thing itself is a type of a בגד, beged, not just
a bandage? Okay, and here there's a debate whether the idea of
יתור בגדים yitur begadim applies to the places on the body which
are not normally where the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna go. רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan says it's not a problem and רבי יהודה בריה דרבי
חייא Rebbi Yehuda brei de-Rebbi Chiya says it is a problem. So
now let's see where the גמרא Gemara continues with this. Okay, ופליגא
דרבא. u-pliga de-Rava. This argues on רבא, Rava, דאמר רבא, de-amar Rava,
אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, במקום בגדים אפילו נימא אחת חוצצת,
bemakom begadim afilu nima achas chotzetzes, שלא במקום בגדים שלש על שלש
חוצצת, shelo bemakom begadim shalosh al shalosh chotzetzes, פחות מכאן אינה חוצצת.
pachos mikan eina chotzetzes. So רבא Rava says the following. He says
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan sounds like if it's מקום בגדים, makom begadim,
like if it was I don't know a bracelet or something, then
it would be a problem because it's an extra בגד. beged. Okay,
right? That's what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan said: the problem of an
extra בגד beged is the place where the כהן kohen wears the
בגד. beged. And comes along רבא Rava and רבא Rava says wait,
he's reminding us of the חציצה. chatzitza. There's a problem of a
חציצה chatzitza not just between your hand and the knife, let's say.
There's a problem of the חציצה chatzitza between your arm and your
tunic, between your clothes and your body, okay? Your clothes have to,
it says על בשרו, al besaro, ולבש, velavash, you know, it says
מכנסי בד יהיו על בשרו. michnesei vad yihyu al besaro. The clothes
have to directly touch the skin. So therefore רבא Rava says is,
if you have something, I don't care if it's a bandage, I
mean according to רבא, Rava, if you had a scratch, right, and
you had a bandage, even though nobody's calling it a בגד, beged,
that's getting between the garment and the and the skin, your skin
it's supposed to be touching. If you had one loose נימא nima
that's sitting there between your garment and the skin, that's a problem.
So רבא Rava says forget the idea of an extra בגד. beged.
Anything where your בגדים begadim are supposed to be that's on your
skin, that's a חציצה. chatzitza. So even one little נימא. nima. Now,
if it is not...
Yeah, like if it's a little frayed... Not frayed, but like, you
know, like sometimes, whatever, you get like a little...
As long as it's still attached, you're fine, but if it actually
came off, it would be a problem. Now, says רבא, Rava, if...
Like here in the מקוה mikvah then, the נימא... nima... What? It's
like here in the מקוה. mikvah. Yeah, the נימא...
nima... Right, right, right. Yeah, it's a very... exactly, it's issues of
חציצה. chatzitza. Okay, and then he says, and if it's שלא במקום
בגדים, shelo bemokom begadim, let's say it's on the back of your
hand. So there רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said it would have to
be, it sounded like what we were saying is it has to
be something that, you know, really is a בגד, beged, like a
type, I don't know, of a bracelet or something. But רבא Rava
is saying, you know, three finger width by three finger width, that's
the amount of cloth that in normal הלכות טומאה וטהרה hilchos tumah
vetaharah is considered to be like a, you know, in the category
of a garment. So therefore what רבא Rava is saying is even
if it's not functionally a garment, even if it is, you know,
as long as it's a big enough piece of material, that's a
problem of ייתור בגדים. yitur begadim. Okay, so what you've got is
the following.
So
the נימא nima doesn't have to be a thread from the clothes,
can actually even be like a hair from your head that fell
off, got on your body, then that'd be a
חציצה.
chatzitza. Correct. Why it's so much... it's like the מקוה. mikvah. Because
as long as it's attached, it's fine, and when it's disconnected
and on your back, then it's not fine. And it's also called
נימא. nima. Right? I don't really remember how far the tunic
goes on his arms, but okay. Alright, so here you go. So
now according to רבא, Rava, okay, according to רבא, Rava, anything that
is here, okay, is a problem of חציצה, chatzitza, and therefore it's
even a נימא. nima. And
anything
that's let's say here,
okay,
that's a problem about ייתור בגדים
yitur
begadim and that's three by three. Okay, that's what רבא Rava says.
Okay, whereas רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say the same distinction except
here he would sort of say that it's not an issue about
חציצה, chatzitza, according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan it's an issue about
ייתור
בגדים
yitur
begadim and it would sound like for him it has to be
a בגד, beged, okay,
as
opposed to here he says it's got to be a נימא. nima.
That's what, that's if it's in this
place, in order to invalidate. Whereas here רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would
say
no
problem
of
ייתור yitur
and
it's all okay. All right?
Why
is it... Because it's שלא במקום בגדים.
shelo bemokom begadim. Okay, so... like if he put it on the
back of his hand.
Yeah,
well yeah, assuming it's not getting between his hand and the עבודה,
avodah, okay, let's assume the back of the hand, okay. So רבא
Rava says here it's a חציצה chatzitza and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says here it's ייתור בגדים. yitur begadim. And here רבא Rava says
it's a problem presumably of ייתור בגדים yitur begadim in three by
three and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it's nothing there and it's
okay. All right, and then you had the first position. Who was
the first position? רב יהודה בריה דרב חייא, Rav Yehuda breih deRav
Chiyya, okay. רב יהודה
בריה
דרב חייא
Rav Yehuda breih
deRav Chiyya sounded like he also disagreed with רבא, Rava, it sounded
like he also, he said it's a problem of, it is a
problem of ייתור, yitur, but it would go by the idea of
a צלצול, tziltzul, right? So it sounds like he was sort of
like in רבא's Rava camp except he wanted there to be a
צלצול tziltzul whereas רבא Rava says it's just... קבלי דמי סבי Kably
d'mei savy goes by size. צלצול's tziltzul like a, you know, like
a type of a... how do they translate צלצול? tziltzul?
They translate it a little bracelet or something.
It has to be something that's a real בגד. beged. Okay so
I should actually
put
him over here, okay. רבא Rava says it's about ייתור בגדים yitur
begadim and here it says רב חייא בריה
דרבא
Rav Chiyya breih deRava was it?
Anyway
so he also says it's about ייתור yitur but he says it's
a צלצול. tziltzul.
רב יהודה בריה דרב חייא. Rav Yehuda breih deRav Chiyya.
Oh my god okay. רב יהודה בריה דרב חייא. Rav Yehuda breih
deRav Chiyya.
Okay, he says it's צלצול. tziltzul. All right, so you got it,
you got three possibilities, you got here if it's out
here. And this is all assuming it's not between your hand and
the עבודה, Avoda, and if it's between your בגד Beged and your
body, רבא Rava says even a tiny string, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says no, it would really have to be a different בגד,
Beged, so whole wide range of positions.
You're only talking about the
right hand and on the left hand they don't care where it
is on the left hand because it's not used? Right, in terms
of that's the other point which I'm not addressing, which is the
חציצה Chatzitza between your skin and the עבודה. Avoda. But yeah, in
my example, it's on the left hand. That was very intentional.
Sorry, this is bothering me about the glasses. You can't say like
because פיקוח נפש, Pikuach Nefesh, don't wear your glasses, you'll get like
hit by a car?
Alright, fine. You, I wear my glasses on שבת Shabbos even without
an עירוב. Eruv. Moving on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: במקום בגדים,
B'makom Begadim, okay,
ופליגי דרבא, U'pligi d'Rava, fine, שלא במקום בגדים שלוש על שלוש חוצצת,
Shelo b'makom begadim shalosh al shalosh chotzetzes, פחות מכאן אינה חוצצת. pachot
mikan eina chotzetzes. Now, by the way, what's disturbing here, not disturbing,
but something to be alerted to, is that the use—and רש"י Rashi
says this throughout the דף—the Daf use of the word חציצה Chatzitza
is sometimes imprecise. If it's talking about between your clothes and the
and your skin or between your skin and the like, I don't
know, the blood, let's say, then חציצה Chatzitza is precise. But sometimes
the word חציצה Chatzitza is used to indicate this idea of יתור
בגדים. Itur Bigadim. So when רבא Rava says when it's three by
three here, it's חוצצת, chotzetzes, he doesn't really mean it's חוצצת, chotzetzes,
he really means it's יתור בגדים. Itur Bigadim. What's it being חוצץ
chotzetz for between when it's three by three? Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אדרבי יוחנן ודאי פליגי. Ad'Rabbi Yochanan vadai pligi.
Now, this position of רבא Rava definitely disagrees with רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says here it's all okay, it's not
a problem of יתור בגדים, Itur Bigadim, and here רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says it's a problem, you need a real בגד, Beged, not
just a string. So there's a strong contrast to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. Okay. What? Is the חציצה Chatzitza not between him and the
like קודש? Kodesh? That also, but that's not what we're talking about.
Let's assume it's like your left hand right now, okay? All right.
So אדרבי יוחנן ודאי פליגי, Ad'Rabbi Yochanan vadai pligi, אדרב יהודה בריה
דרב חייא מי לימא דפליגי? ad'Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav Chiya mi leima
d'pligi? So should we say he disagrees? Because רב יהודה בריה דרב
חייא Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav Chiya says here it's got it's a
צלצול Tziltzul and he says here it's three by three, they seem
to be debating what constitutes a בגד. Beged. So the גמרא Gemara
says no: שאני צלצול קטן דחשיב. Shani tziltzul katan d'chashiv. No, they
could agree. He could say if it's a little bracelet, even if
it's small, if it's if it's big, like one of two things
could define it as a בגד: Beged: function or size. And it
could be they're not debating. You've got it on the back of
your hand or whatever your left hand, it's not where your בגד
Beged is, it's not a question of חציצה, Chatzitza, it's a question
of an extra בגד. Beged. What defines an extra בגד? Beged? So
it could be they're both giving two ways to define extra בגד.
Beged. One is functionally, it's a little, it's a bracelet, even if
it's small, like a ring and a ring or whatever. And the
other says if it's a if it's a piece of cloth, even
if functionally it's not a בגד, Beged, if it's big enough, that
constitutes a בגד. Beged. Okay, so these are two variations of a
בגד. Beged. Got it? Okay, so here he says, רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says no יתור בגדים, Itur Bigadim, and this says within יתור
בגדים, Itur Bigadim, let's put it this way, okay, this is the
approach that says there's a problem of יתור בגדים Itur Bigadim on
that part, and right and who was it? רבא Rava says it
goes by three by three and who was it? רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda whatever says it goes by צלצול. Tziltzul. So those are two
variations of how to define something as a בגד Beged on that
part. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no problem. Okay, and here
רבא Rava says there's a חציצה Chatzitza issue and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says there's only a יתור בגדים Itur Bigadim issue. Good? Everybody
got it? Okay, it'll be on the final. Let's keep on going.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
But יתור בגדים Itur Bigadim also has to be like a three
by three, right?
For רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan over here, presumably. Okay, or some other
definition. Right. Okay. לישנא אחרינא, Lishana Acharina, here's another variation of this
debate. אמרי לה. Amrei lah. אמר רב יהודה בריה דרב חייא: Amar
Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav Chiya: לא שנו אלא גמי אבל צלצול קטן
חוצץ. Lo shanu ela gami aval tziltzul katan chotzetz. That's the same
thing, although here he switched to a language of חוצץ, chotzetz, רש"י
Rashi makes the point that he's really again being interchangeable with יתור
בגדים. Itur Bigadim. So this is the same version, okay, that he's
saying it's a צלצול, Tziltzul, okay, it's only a צלצול Tziltzul is
going to be a problem on the hand.
ורבי יוחנן אמר לא אמרו חציצה בפחות משלוש על שלוש אלא במקום
בגדים, V'Rabbi Yochanan amar lo amru chatzitza b'pachot mi'shalosh al shalosh ela
b'makom begadim, אבל שלא במקום בגדים שלוש על שלוש חוצצת פחות מכאן
אינה חוצצת. aval shelo b'makom begadim shalosh al shalosh chotzetzes pachot mikan
eina chotzetzes. So in this version,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan actually is pretty is basically like רבא. Rava.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying במקום בגדים B'makom Begadim even less
than three by three. So according to this version of רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, okay, I don't know if I should erase the previous
one, but anyway, according to this version of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
it's like even tiny, even tiny, less than three by three, which
is basically the same as רבא. Rava. If it's where your בגדים
begadim are, even a small— thing, it's a חציצה. chatzitzah. But if
it's not where your בגדים begadim are, now according to this version
of ר' יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, he's saying three by three, which is
also the same thing as רבא. Rava. So according to this version,
ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is basically saying the same thing as רבא.
Rava. Okay, שלא במקום בגדים shelo bimkom begadim less than three by
three,
במקום בגדים bimkom begadim it's three by three. The only difference is
is that he is saying this as a way of disagreeing with
ר' יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. So ר' יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is saying that
here a little bracelet is a problem, and what רבא Rava is
really doing is רבא... Rava, I mean ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is
really doing is ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is saying, no, ר' יהודה,
Rebbi Yehuda, a little bracelet isn't a problem. You all... anything less
than three by three is not an issue. Okay, so according to
this version, ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is basically the same as רבא,
Rava. but what the point of what he's saying is is that
a צלצול tziltzul is not enough. It needs to be three by
three.
Right, so the גמרא Gemara says the following.
ר' יוחנן אמר לא שנו אלא חציצה פחות משלוש על שלוש שלא
במקום בגדים אבל במקום בגדים אפילו פחות משלוש על שלוש נמי מקשה,
Rebbi Yochanan amar lo
shanu ela chatzitzah pachot mishalosh al shalosh shelo bimkom begadim aval bimkom
begadim afilu pachot mishalosh al shalosh nami mikasha, והיינו דרבא, ve'hainu de'Rava,
which is effectively the same as רבא. Rava אמר רב חסדא לימא
פליגא אדרבי יהודה בריה דרבי חייא. Amar Rav Chisda leima pliga ad'Rebbi
Yehuda brei de'Rebbi Chiya. So now we know that ר' יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan argues on ר' יהודה Rebbi Yehuda because ר' יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
says צלצול, tziltzul, ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says צלצול tziltzul isn't enough.
You need three by three. Should we say that רבא Rava disagrees
with ר' יהודה Rebbi Yehuda because רבא Rava wasn't talking to ר'
יהודה? Rebbi Yehuda? These two ideas don't have to contradict, like we
said before, they could be different ways of defining a בגד. beged.
From context, it's clear that ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan, rejects this way
and says you need a minimum. But the גמרא Gemara is saying,
should we assume that רבא Rava, also rejects that definition? And we've
already answered that. The answer is no. So גמרא Gemara says no,
שאני צלצול קטן דחשיב. shani tziltzul katan dechashev. A צלצול קטן, tziltzul
katan, everybody could agree these are alternate definitions: size or something that's
a real בגד. beged. Okay, ולרבי יוחנן מאי איריא גמי? u'le'Rebbi Yochanan
mai irya gemi? Now according to ר' יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan why when
the משנה Mishna in הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos was talking about that
you could put a גמי gemi on, why didn't the משנה Mishna
say you could even put on a little bit of a צלצול,
tziltzul, like a little bracelet? For ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan that would
be okay as long as it's not three by three, right? ר'
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says anything less, according to this version, less than
three by three is not a problem over here, even a real
בגד. beged. So why didn't the משנה Mishna in שבת Shabbos use
that example and tell me you could put even a real בגד
beged here
because it was so small? So the גמרא Gemara says no, מילתא
אגב אורחיה קמשמע לן דגמי מסי. milta agav urchia kamashma lan de'gemi
masi. Because it's talking in הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos context, it's not
talking in an עבודת בית המקדש avodas Beis HaMikdash context, and it
wants to tell you that this type of a גמי, gemi, a
bandage, actually heals. And because it heals, it's allowed in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash but it's not allowed outside the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. Its interest was talking about bandages, its interest wasn't along the
way let me tell you a חידוש chiddush in בגדי כהונה bigdei
kehuna that if you had a bracelet there it would also be
okay. It's like, alright, whatever. That's not the point, what was the
bandage. Alright, so I'm going to erase this other ר' יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan because it effectively is the same as the earlier רבא, Rava
but these are the basic positions, okay?
רבא Rava. says a tiny string here is a problem, which one
version of ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan said the same. But ר' יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan says, no, if it's on where the בגדים begadim are,
you need a real בגד. beged. If it's not where the בגדים
begadim are, according to the old version, ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan would
say no problem at all. Here they're saying it would be an
issue, but it has to be defined as a בגד. beged. What's
defined as a בגד? beged? Either a certain size or
functionally. Alright, and the only thing we introduced was a version of
ר' יוחנן which is effectively the same as רבא.
Rava Yes, is the issue is healing, why would it be allowed
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and not outside?
Because you don't do רפואה refuah on שבת. Shabbos.
Right, but why would they allow...
that's what we said at the very beginning, that they gave a
basic waiver for rabbinic restrictions on שבת Shabbos in the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. Alright, because there's an assumption, like I said, either that
כהנים kohanim are careful, and anyway you're allowing all this other עבודה
avoda to be done on שבת Shabbos in the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, right, you know, שחיטה shechita and whatever by the קרבנות korbanos
that you're bringing on שבת. Shabbos. So it's so you know, it's
ironic because it's the holiest place and the holiest day and you're
giving this license. But somehow, and the holiest people, but maybe that's
why. You can trust them to keep to the דאורייתא d'Oraisa rule
and you don't have to add extra prohibitions of the rabbinic ones.
But I just don't... what does healing have to do with anything?
Because you're not allowed... the same way it's... oh, it's rabbinic. It's
a concern that you would come to grind medicine. It's like why
we don't take... you know, why we don't take medicine unless it's
a, you know, unless people are, you know, sick in a... you
know, for like a trivial type of a headache or whatever you're
not supposed to take medicine on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, and that's how
Jesus got in trouble because he did healing on the Sabbath day.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, now when
not... the only reason he got in trouble, he was violating דרבנן.
de'Rabbanan. I mean, okay, anyway. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: בעי רבא. Ba'ei Rava. Now רבא asks, now we're going to
have some fun. Okay, what exactly constitutes a חציצה chatzitzah between your
garment and your skin? נכנסה לו רוח בבגדו מהו? Nichnesa lo ruach
bevigdo mahu?
A wind came and lifted, you know, your tunic a little bit
off from your leg, so it's not directly touching the skin of
your leg, okay? Imagine, again, it's like a toga and a tunic.
It's not pants or whatever. So על בשרו בעינן, Al besaro ba’inan,
does it have to literally be touching the skin? והא ליכא, Veha
lika, and you don’t have it. או דילמא דרך לבישה בכך? O
dilma derech levisha bekach? Or give me a break, there’s not a
חציצה. chatzitzah. Nobody’s saying it has to literally every single inch of
the garment has to touch every single inch of your skin. That’s
just the normal way of wearing. Sometimes it’s touching physically against the
skin, sometimes it’s a little removed, there’s a little air space and
that’s not a problem. Obviously that’s the only logical thing to say.
How could you get a tunic that’s so tight-fitting that every, that
it’s constantly up against the skin of all parts of the skin?
Anyway, so that’s one question. כינה מהו שתחלוץ? Kinah mahu shetachlotz? Let’s
say you’ve got a little louse that’s on your skin. Okay, welcome
to the hygienic realities of that time. What? נידה. Niddah. נידה, Niddah,
yeah.
Right, exactly. מתה לא תיבעי לך. Metah lo tiba’i lach. If it’s
a dead louse, I don’t have any question. דבר חציצה. Devar chatzitzah.
It definitely is a problem. It’s something you wouldn’t want on your
body and you would get rid of and so on. חיה מאי?
Chayah mai? What’s the story if it’s a living louse?
מי אמרינן כיון דאזלא ואתיא רביתא היא? Mi amrinan keivan de’azla ve’atya
ravita hi? Do we say that since it’s coming and
going, it’s רביתא היא? ravita hi? And Rashi says an interesting thing.
He says like it’s like it’s part of your skin. Of course
the fact is that it will go away by itself, it’s specifically
not part of your skin. But anyway, it’s not considered to be
something that’s really present and a problem, ולא חוצץ. velo chotzetz. או
דילמא כיון דקפיד עליה חוצצת? O dilma keivan dekapid aleih chotzetzet? Obviously
you don’t want it there, it is a חציצה. chatzitzah. עפר מהו
שתחלוץ? Afar mahu shetachlotz? How about if you’ve got dirt on your
skin? עפר ודאי חוצץ. Afar vadai chotzetz. What do you mean? That’s
definitely a חציצה. chatzitzah. אלא אבק עפר מהו? Ella avak afar mahu?
Let’s say it’s a very fine dust or not an obvious dirt.
בית השחי מהו שתחלוץ? Beit hashechi mahu shetachlotz?
Now how about if it’s like this area right here? And again,
this is a problem just of the air. So it’s one thing
if my tunic is against my legs and every now and then
a little bit removed, it’s one thing, but here the way the
garment is made, right, naturally there’s always going to be like an
air space. So what kind of question is that? It means you
can never be a כהן. Kohen. No, so Rashi said maybe you
have to cut it so that it’s tight up against and it’s
form-fitting against the underarm. That also restricts the movement of the Levi'im
and their ability to do the עבודה.
Avodah.
I know, right. Some of these questions you think like the answer's
got to be it's okay, or how did they function? Let me
just finish it. על בשרו בעינן והא ליכא או דילמא דרך לבישה
בכך. Al besaro ba’inan veha lika o dilma derech levisha bekach. Okay,
normally if the דרך לבישה בכך, derech levisha bekach, you assume that's
the right answer. Okay, let's just read a couple more and then
I'll get back to you. הכניס ידו לתוך חיקו מהו? Hichnis yado
letoch cheiko mahu? Let's say you put your hand in here, between
your garment. It's very specific as to how you do it. I
assume you only got, right, there's not like a thing down here.
You have to go through like that or something. I don't know
exactly how you did it. But some part of your own body
is between the tunic and your skin. גופו מי חייץ? Gufo michai?
Does your body, is it a חציצה chatzitzah against your body itself?
או לאו? O lav? Or not? נימא מהו שתחלוץ? Nima mahu shetachlotz?
How about if you have a string of the garment? What's the
story? Now we dealt with that before. So the Gemara says נימא
ודאי חוצץ. Nima vadai chotzetz. What do you mean? It’s definitely a
חציצה. chatzitzah. I mean it’s definitely a חציצה chatzitzah according to like
Rava here, but okay. אלא נימא מדובללת מהו? Ella nima meduvlelet mahu?
Let's say it's a string from the garment that's like hanging, like
what Michael asked. It's still technically attached to the garment but it's
hanging. בעי מר בר רב אשי. Ba’ei Mar bar Rav Ashi. יצא
שערו בבגדו מהו? Yatza se’aro bevigdo mahu? Let’s say you’ve got nice
long hair, you’ve got a nice ponytail as a כהן, Kohen, or
I don’t know what the case is.
Because this would be פרע ראש, pera rosh, right? Isn’t the פרע
ראש pera rosh anything longer than thirty days?
Your hair won't get that long in less than thirty days.
I don't know, I mean you can cut your hair. What, you
don't have to cut it bald. You give yourself a haircut, but
even if you give yourself a haircut, if you cut it just
to where it went and then it grows more and, it's a
good question. I mean you can trim it, but what doesn't mean
you have to cut it back to the scalp. I don't know
the answer to that, I have to look into it. But I
don't think, it means you can't let it grow un-groomed and un-cut.
So you keep on cutting it, but it keeps on growing. You
just cut. Anyway, okay, so you've got a nice little ponytail going
here and it gets between your tunic and your, and like your,
and the back
and your
skin. יצא שערו בבגדו מהו? Yatza se’aro bevigdo mahu? שיער כגופו דמי.
Se’ar kegupo dami. Is that like your body, assuming that your hand
wouldn't be a חציצה? chatzitzah? או לאו כגופו דמי? O lav kegupo
dami? Or is it less like your body and more of a
חציצה? chatzitzah? בעי רב זירא. Ba’ei Rav Zeira. Okay, and so what,
just pause here for a second, you had a question, Michael?
No, not a question, how to think about it. We were talking
yesterday after the דף daf that like, I thought the army uniform
is an example, and then David took it one step higher, double
meaning, to astronauts. Right. Because like the כהנים Kohanim go into a
holy of holies place. Right. So you wouldn't send
an astronaut to space and be like, it's okay if there's a
little air here and a little air there. Right, right, right. But
we find don't understand where they're going into but if we could
think, you know, same as soldiers, you wouldn't be like, hey, your
helmet is kind of...
right, right, right. That's a good analogy. Good.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay. My baby Zebra.
תפילין משה יחוצו. Tefillin Moshe Yachotzu. How about תפילין? tefillin? Okay. Now
here רש"י Rashi says the question isn't about חציצה. chatzitzah. I mean
there should be תפילין tefillin של יד shel yad and של ראש.
shel rosh. של יד shel yad could be a חציצה chatzitzah problem.
But רש"י Rashi says that basically the question at this stage, although
the way you never know when it uses the word חציצה, chatzitzah,
but רש"י Rashi says that basically the question is is it an
extra בגד? begged? Sort of like my question about wearing eyeglasses. Is
wearing תפילין tefillin an extra בגד? begged? Let's talk about the של
ראש. shel rosh. Okay. So אליבא דמאן דאמר לילה לאו זמן תפילין
היא, aliba deman d'amar layla lav zman tefillin hee, if לילה layla
is not the time of the מצוה mitzvah of תפילין, tefillin, so
לא תיבעי לך, lo tibay lach, then there's no question. It's obviously
an extra בגד. begged. כיון דלילה חייץ יום נמי חייץ. keivan de'layla
chaitz yom nami chaitz. Since at night it's an extra בגד, begged,
right, you're just it doesn't count as a מצוה mitzvah or whatever,
then presumably רש"י Rashi says since the day עבודה avodah anyway is
more weightier than the night עבודה, avodah, anyway, since there's times when
it's considered to be just a בגד begged then even during the
day it's just some extra בגד begged and it's a problem. כי
תיבעי לך, ki tibay lach, what's the question? למאן דאמר לילה זמן
תפילין. leman d'amar layla zman tefillin. So yes, you can always be
wearing תפילין tefillin and always be doing a מצוה. mitzvah. So therefore
do we say that when you're wearing it it's like a type
of a מצוה mitzvah object or do we say it's an extra
בגד? begged? רש"י Rashi says maybe because it's a מצוה mitzvah it
should be considered like to be part of your body. I don't
exactly understand that. But anyway, I will frame it as do we
view this as a מצוה mitzvah or do we view this as
a בגד? begged? So what do you say? מאי? mai? מצוה דגופיה
חייץ או לא
חייץ? mitzvah degupei chaitz o lo chaitz? Is it something that's a
מצוה, mitzvah, is that considered a חציצה chatzitzah or okay the way
רש"י Rashi would say it an extra בגד begged or not an
extra בגד? begged? איגלגל מילתא, igagual milsa, so there was a transmigration
of souls, no sorry, okay the matter the matter rolled around ומטא
לקמיה דרבי אמי u'mata lekamei d'Rabbi Ami and it came to רבי
אמי. Rabbi Ami. אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said, תלמוד ערוך
הוא בידינו, talmud aruch hu beyadeinu,
we have a long stead teaching תפילין חוצצת. tefillin chotzetzet. It is
a problem. מיתיבי, meisivei, now you don't know maybe that's because לילה
לאו זמן תפילין, layla lav zman tefillin, but okay. מיתיבי, meisivei, I'll
ask you on this. כהנים בעבודתם ולוים בדוכנם וישראל במעמדם. Kohanim ba'avodatam
u'Leviim b'duchanam v'Yisrael b'ma'amadam.
So we've got a ברייתא braitat that teaches when the כהנים Kohanim
are doing their עבודה avodah and the לוים Leviim are on their
platform doing their you know singing and their musical instruments and the
ישראל Yisrael are there representing the people and standing over the
קרבנות, korbanot, פטורים מן התפילין. peturim min ha'tefillin. So they're עוסק במצוה
osek bemitzvah and they don't have to דאוון daven and they don't
have to wear תפילין. tefillin. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו,
mai lav, so it sounds like they're exempt but it sounds like
if they were to wear תפילין tefillin it wouldn't invalidate. מאי לאו
אם הניחם אינם חוצצת. mai lav im henicham einam chotzetzet. It sounds
like if they were to wear it it wouldn't invalidate the עבודה.
avodah. Says לא אם הניחם חוצצת. lo im henicham chotzetzet. No, I'll
tell you if the כהן Cohen would wear it it would invalidate.
אי הכי, i hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, פטורים, peturim, it shouldn't
say they're exempt from תפילין, tefillin, אסורין מיבעי ליה, asurin mibei lei,
should say they're not allowed to wear תפילין. tefillin. So the גמרא
Gemara says no כיון דאיכא לוים וישראל דלא מפסלו ליה, keivan de'ika
Leviim v'Yisrael d'lo masnu lei, since by the לוים Leviim and ישראל
Yisrael it couldn't say they're forbidden. By the לוים Leviim and ישראל
Yisrael it's just saying they're exempt, there's nothing that's forbidden for them.
So דלא מפסלו ליה, d'lo masnu lei, couldn't say אסור, asur, משום
הכי תנא פטורים. mishum hachi tana peturim. That's why it says that
they're exempt. But the reality is that were a כהן Cohen to
wear it, it wouldn't just be that he's not obligated, it would
actually invalidate because it would be an extra בגד. begged. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute ותניא אם הניחם אינם חוצצים, v'tanya im
henicham einam chotzetzim, we've got a חוצצת, chotzetzet, we have an explicit
ברייתא. braitat. The ברייתא braitat teaches that if they did wear it
it's not a חציצה. chatzitzah. So you said we have a long
stead teaching it is, I've got a ברייתא braitat that says it
isn't a חציצה. chatzitzah. So לא קשיא הא דיד הא דראש. lo
kashya ha de'yad ha de'rosh. Ah, difference of a תפילין tefillin של
יד shel yad של ראש. shel rosh. And now basically we're saying
it is a חציצה chatzitzah problem. You wear the תפילין tefillin של
יד shel yad that's a חציצה, chatzitzah, gets between the בגד begged
and your skin. You wear the תפילין tefillin של ראש shel rosh
we're not going to consider it an extra בגד begged and it's
not a חציצה chatzitzah because it's not getting between any בגד. begged.
Okay, so it sounded like initially we were saying it's an extra
בגד, begged, now we're saying it's not an extra בגד, begged, it's
a חציצה. chatzitzah. And because it's a חציצה chatzitzah it's only a
problem of the של יד shel yad not the של ראש. shel
rosh. The גמרא Gemara says now מאי שנא דיד דכתיב וילבש על
בשרו שלא יהא דבר חוצץ בינו ולבשרו? mai shna de'yad de'ksiv ulvash
al besaro shelo yei davar chotzetz beino l'vesaro? So the problem of
the של יד shel yad is חציצה chatzitzah not an extra בגד.
begged. So says the גמרא Gemara דראש נמי כתיב ושמת המצנפת על
ראשו? de'rosh nami ksiv v'samta hamitznefet al rosho? So one of the
בגדים begadim we forgot about was the miter was the you know
the cap that the כהן Cohen wears. So there can't be a
חציצה chatzitzah there either. So how are you going to get so
how are you going to do it? So the גמרא Gemara says
no תנא שערו היה נראה בין ציץ למצנפת. tana searo hayah nir'eh
bein tzitz l'mitznefet. No, because the מצנפת mitznefet would not cover the
whole hair, there would normally by the כהן גדול Cohen Gadol right
he'd have the ציץ tzitz the gold plate on the forehead and
he'd have the מצנפת mitznefet and it'd be a little bit of
of you know of hair sticking out between the two. And that's
a כהן גדול Cohen Gadol has a ציץ tzitz other כהנים Kohanim
don't have a ציץ tzitz obviously. But what it means is that
the מצנפת mitznefet doesn't cover the whole hair, doesn't cover the whole
skull, it ends over here. And if it ends over here you're
able to put your תפילין tefillin right over here without there being
a חציצה. chatzitzah. Okay, presumably it also means in the back you're
able to get the straps. in a way that they don't get
in the way either. Okay, היה נראה בין ציץ למצנפת ושם מניחין
תפילין. haya nireh bein tzitz lemitznefes vesham manichin tefillin. There you put
the תפילין. Tefillin. Okay, so that's our basic answer, תפילין Tefillin is
not an extra בגד, beged, it's only a חציצה chatzitzah problem and
therefore it's only a problem by the של ראש. shel rosh. And
with that we're done with the discussion of extra בגדים begadim and
חציצה chatzitzah and so on. I thought that was a lot of
fun. Now we go on to other types of things that invalidate
and the next line of the משנה Mishnah is מחוסר כיפורים, mechusar
kippurim, somebody who hasn't brought a קרבן korban as part of the
טהרה taharah process. We had a whole discussion about right, מחוסר כיפורים
mechusar kippurim דזב כזב דמי dezav kezav dami and, you know, מחוסר
mechusar and הערב שמש ha'erev shemesh or whatever, טבול יום. tvul yom.
And so the גמרא Gemara here deals with it very, very, you
know, succinctly. מנלן? menalan? אמר רב הונא אמר קרא וכיפר עליה הכהן
וטהרה. amar Rav Huna amar kra vechiper aleha hakohen vetaherah. The כהן
kohen should atone for her and she should become טהורה. tehorah. This
is I think about the יולדת. yoledes. So מכלל טהורה מכלל שהיא
טמאה. mikh'lal tehorah mikh'lal she'hee tmeiah. Until she finishes the process she's
considered טמאה tmeiah until the final קרבן korban is brought. And therefore
since we already learned that a טמא tamei person invalidates the עבודה
avodah and this is included in she's still considered בגברא begavra as
we would say in terms of her personal status as being טמאה,
tmeiah, so therefore it invalidates the עבודה avodah as well. Okay, so
now moving on to a new point.
Were you answering all those questions?
No, they're open-ended questions. Yeah. Okay, yeah, it didn't even bother saying
תיקו. teiku. It was just clear that they were just speculating that
we weren't going to answer them. Okay, ושלא רחוץ ידים ורגלים, veshelo
rachutz yadayim veraglayim, somebody who did not wash the hands and the
feet that a כהן kohen does at the beginning of the day,
that also invalidates. Okay, so the גמרא, Gemara, do you know that?
אתיא חוקה חוקה atya chukka chukka from מחוסר בגדים, mechusar begadim, we
had this yesterday when Michal did it, because it says by that
חוקת עולם chukas olam and so on that, and that links it
to lacking בגדים, begadim, and lacking בגדים begadim invalidates because it says
like because of, you know, when they're not wearing the בגדים begadim
it's like they're not כהנים. kohanim. So, and therefore not washing hands
is linked by the word חוק chok to not wearing בגדים begadim
and therefore we know it also invalidates. Okay, so now תנו רבנן.
tanu rabanan. Now we're going to have some fun discussing this issue
about what type of washing invalidates or does not invalidate. כהן גדול
שלא טבל ושלא קידש בין בגד לבגד ובין עבודה לעבודה. Kohen Gadol
shelo taval veshelo kidesh bein beged lebeged uvein avodah la'avodah. So on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would switch his
clothes five times, actually switch them four times, he'd wear five different,
well, okay, from let's say his בגדי חול. bigdei chol. He'd switch
his clothes five times and between each switching he would go to
the מקוה mikvah and wash his hands before and after going to
the מקוה mikvah or before after changing clothes. So ten
washing
of hands, five going to the מקואות. mikvaos. If he washed his
hands at the beginning of the day of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
but then between each change of clothes he did not do this
מקוה mikvah and washing of the hands, so the הלכה halachah is
that even though that's part of the עבודה avodah of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and you know it
says ורחץ את בשרו במים ולבשם, verachatz es besaro bamayim velavasham, it
even describes it explicitly, talks about going to the מקוה, mikvah, you
know ורחץ את בשרו, verachatz es besaro, bathing your, you know, immersing
your body in water and so on, nevertheless it does not prevent
the עבודה avodah from being good. If you don't do the interim
מקואות mikvaos and washing of the hands. כהן גדול שלא טבל ושלא
קידש בין בגד לבגד, Kohen Gadol shelo taval veshelo kidesh bein beged
lebeged, if you don't go to the מקוה, mikvah, wash the hands
between clothes, ובין עבודה לעבודה, uvein avodah la'avodah, ועבד, ve'avad, and you
did the עבודה avodah on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, עבודתו כשירה, avodaso
ksheirah, it's still valid. ואחד כהן גדול ואחד כהן הדיוט שלא קידש
ידיו ורגליו שחרית ועבד עבודתו פסולה. ve'echad Kohen Gadol ve'echad Kohen Hedyot
shelo kidesh yadav veraglav shacharis ve'avad avodaso psulah. But if anybody, כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol or a normal כהן, kohen, doesn't do the initial
washing of hands and feet in the morning, that's our teaching of
our משנה, Mishnah, then the עבודה avodah is invalid. Okay, so that's
not the חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is that the washings between
the changes of clothes, the extra washings of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
does not invalidate. Now you say obviously like there's no special פסוק
pasuk to say it invalidates, but the גמרא Gemara is going to
say one minute, our default assumption is that any parts of the
יום כיפור עבודה Yom Kippur avodah that aren't done invalidate because it
says חוק chok by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, חוקת עולם chukas olam
and whatever and that means that every single detail of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur if you don't do it it prevents it from working,
from being valid. So why does this not invalidate on יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רב
אסי לרבי יוחנן. amar lei Rav Assi leRabbi Yochanan. So רב אסי
Rav Assi said to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan מכדי michdi let's take
a
look. חמש טבילות ועשרה קידושין דאורייתא. chamesh tvilos va'asarah kiddushin d'Oraisa. The
going to the מקוה mikvah five times and washing the hand ten
times we understand that that's a biblical requirement. וחוק כתיב בהו vechok
ksiv behu and it says by יום כיפור Yom Kippur it says
חוק chok לעכב le'akev which means that every single one, every single
detail of יום כיפור Yom Kippur if you don't do it it
prevents it from working. אמר ליה amar lei so רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said back אמר קרא amar kra the verse says
ולבשם. velavasham. It says ורחץ את בשרו במים ולבשם. verachatz es besaro
bamayim velavasham. It says by יום כיפור Yom Kippur you know wash
your skin with water, go to the מקוה mikvah and wear the
garment. So the extra fact that it repeated ולבשם velavasham because before
that it said ולבש הכהן מדו בד ומכנסי בד יהיו על בשרו
ואבנט בד יחגור ובמצנפת בד יצנוף בגדי קודש הם ורחץ את בשרו
במים ולבשם. velavash hakohen mido vad umikhnesai vad yihyu al besaro ve'avneit
vad yachgor uvmitznefes vad yitznof bigdei kodesh heim verachatz es besaro bamayim
velavasham. So after this whole list of dress all these wear this
and this and this and this, it says go to the מקוה
mikvah and wear them. So why did it repeat wearing them after
it just had this whole long list of everything you're supposed to
wear? So he says to tell you לבישה מעכבת ואין דבר אחר
מעכב. levishah me'akeves ve'ein davar acher me'akev. The repetition of ולבשם velavasham
in the פסוק pasuk that talks about going to the מקוה. mikvah.
It's just to tell you in this פסוק pasuk the only thing
that prevents it from working is the wearing of the garments. The
actual going to the מקוה mikvah between them does not prevent it
from working, okay? So the extra, the repetition of ולבשם ulvasham said
that לבישה levisha is what matters and not the going to the
מקוה. mikvah. ואין דבר אחר מעכב. ve'ein davar acheir me'akeiv. צהבו פניו
tzahavu fanav of רב אשי Rav Ashi like his face lit up,
I love that expression. Oh, that's such a brilliant read of the
פסוק. pasuk. That's great! It repeats ולבשם ulvasham and it right there
speaks about רחיצה rechitza to tell you רחיצה rechitza isn't as important
as the לבישה. levisha. He loved the answer. So רב יוחנן Rav
Yochanan says, אמר ליה, amar lei, וו עופסא כתיבי לך? vav aufsa
kesivi lach?
So this is some type of idiomatic expression. It means what, did
I write a letter וו vav for you on like a, on
a valley or whatever a בקע, bika, you know, which is like
what? It's sort of like did I write it on a rock
or? רש"י Rashi basically says if you try to write something on
a, how do they translate it there?
On a wood log.
A wood log, alright. Anyway, if you try to write like a,
take some ink and a quill and try to write on a
wood log, the letter's going to be all cracked and messy or
whatever. So it's some type of a way of saying like what,
you think this is a good answer? That was a lousy answer.
Or you know, anyway, but some weird idiomatic expression. Try to write
a וו vav on, you know, you think I wrote for you
a וו vav on a log? So
anyway, which means like what, you think that was a good answer?
So וו עופסא כתיבי לך, vav aufsa kesivi lach, did I write
for you a וו vav on a log? אי הכי, ei hachi,
if that was a good answer, דצפרא נמי, detzafra nami, so I
should say that even the, even the washing of the hands of
the morning shouldn't be מעכב me'akeiv because the פסוק pasuk is downplaying
the idea of the, you know, of going to the מקוה. mikvah.
Of course, I don't know, no, I mean, that doesn't bother me
at all. The going, the washing of the hands in the morning
is a general requirement of all כהנים, kohanim, that clearly is מעכב.
me'akeiv. When the פסוק pasuk here talks about ורחץ בשרו במים ולבשם,
verachatz besaro bamayim ulvasham, it's talking about the extra washings of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur and that's not מעכב. me'akeiv. You gotta feel bad,
you know, here רב אשי Rav Ashi was so happy and satisfied
with the answer and then רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan punctured it right
after he gave it and actually seems like a totally fine answer.
Okay, but רב יוחנן's Rav Yochanan like no, if that was a
good answer then you shouldn't even have to do it in the
morning, wouldn't be מעכב. me'akeiv. So אי הכי דצפרא נמי. ei hachi
detzafra nami. אמר חזקיה אמר קרא, amar Chizkiyah amar kra, so here's
how, so now we're going to learn it from a different פסוק.
pasuk. No, the verse says והיתה
להם חק עולם לו ולזרעו לדורותם. vehaysa lahem chok olam lo ulezaro
ledorosam. It says this by the, in the פסוק pasuk that talks
about making the כיור kiyor and washing from it in the morning.
It says it will be for them an eternal edict for him,
for אהרן Aharon and his children for all future generations. So דבר
המעכב בזרעו מעכב בו. davar hame'akeiv bizaro me'akeiv bo. The thing that
is, that applies to normal כהנים kohanim that prevents the עבודה avoda
from being good, the first washing, that also is true by the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. דבר שאינו מעכב בזרעו, davar she'eino me'akeiv bizaro,
other washings which is never a problem by other כהנים, kohanim, אינו
מעכב בו eino me'akeiv bo is also not something that is a
problem with the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So basically we learn from
the fact that we know that the washing in the morning is,
prevents for all כהנים, kohanim, and from this פסוק pasuk we learn
that's the only thing that prevents it from working even for the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Even on יום כיפור Yom Kippur the only
thing that is going to, the only washing that will prevent it
from being a good עבודה avoda will be the morning washing, not
the interim washings. Okay, דבר שאינו מעכב בו אינו מעכב בו. davar
she'eino me'akeiv bo eino me'akeiv bo. רב יוחנן ורבי יונתן. Rav Yochanan
veRabbi Yonasan. Now, okay, that's one answer. רבי יונתן אומר, Rabbi Yonasan
omer, רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonasan says a similar פסוק pasuk מהכא. meihacha.
ורחצו ממנו משה ואהרן ובניו, verachatzu mimenu Moshe veAharon uvanav, they shall
wash their hands from it, משה ואהרן ובניו, Moshe veAharon uvanav, so
when משה Moshe was doing the עבודה, avoda, you know, during the
seven days of מלואים. miluim. דבר המעכב בבניו, davar hame'akeiv bevanav, a
similar דרשה, drasha, מעכב בו. me'akeiv bo. So it says משה ואהרן
ובניו. Moshe veAharon uvanav. Some, a washing that is necessary for his
sons is necessary for אהרן. Aharon. דבר שאינו מעכב בבניו, davar she'eino
me'akeiv bevanav, a washing that's not a problem for the sons, washings
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur which are not relevant for the sons,
so אינו מעכב בו, eino me'akeiv bo, if the כהן Kohen misses
the interim washings on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it also does not
prevent the עבודה avoda from working. Now, רבי יונתן מאי טעמא לא
אמר מדחזקיה? Rabbi Yonasan mai ta'ama lo amar miDechizkiyah? Now why did
רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonasan not say the פסוק pasuk of חזקיה, Chizkiyah,
the פסוק pasuk of והיתה להם חק עולם, vehaysa lahem chok olam,
which I mean, it seems like one פסוק pasuk or the other
they're pretty much the same? So לא אמר מדחזקיה. lo amar miDechizkiyah.
אמר
לך, amar lach, הוא לדורות הוא דכתיבי. hu ledoros hu dikesivi. That's
not telling you the question of מעכב, me'akeiv, that's just telling you
for all future generations כהנים kohanim are supposed to be washing their
hands. But it's not coming to tell you this extra הלכה halacha
that it's only the morning washing which is the issue.
ואידך מאי טעמא לא אמר מהאי? ve'idach mai ta'ama lo amar me'hai?
And why did, you know, and why did חזקיה Chizkiyah not say
רבי יונתן's Rabbi Yonasan פסוק pasuk of משה ואהרן ובניו? Moshe veAharon
uvanav? So ואידך מאי טעמא לא אמר מהאי, ve'idach mai ta'ama lo
amar me'hai, מיבעי ליה לכדרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא miba'ei lei lechiDeRabbi Yose
beRabbi Chanina to teach you this teaching. דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא,
de'amar Rabbi Yose beRabbi Chanina, כל כיור שאין בו כדי לקדש ארבעה
כהנים ממנו, kol kiyor she'ein bo kedei lekadesh arba'ah kohanim mimenu, any
type of a, of a laver that is not big enough, is
that what they call it, a laver? Anyway, for four כהנים kohanim
to use it at the same time, okay, אין מקדשין בו, ein
mikadshin bo, you is not legitimate for
you. So since those are four people, you have to be big
enough for four כהנים *kohanim* to use it simultaneously. Okay, fine. Anyway,
we learned that it's only the morning that is מעכב me'akeiv, *me'akev*,
not the ones of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. רבי Rebbi יוחנן *Rebbe
Yochanan* gave a great פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, the repetition of ולבשם *u'levasham*,
which downplays the interim washing. And then for some reason he punctured
it, so then we went ahead and we learned it from these
other פסוקים *psukim* that it's only the things that are—only the washings
that are מעכב *me'akev* for the regular כהנים *kohanim*. Yes.
Why aren't they suggesting perhaps that the פסוק pasuk. *posuk* once the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *kohen gadol* is going to go into the
Holy of Holies, that he needs those extra—that's all preparation for that
special—that would be what we would have assumed. And also the use
of the word חוק *chok* would have assumed that everything is required,
which is why we need an extra פסוק pasuk *posuk* to teach
me that it's not the case. Okay, תנו *tanu*. Now, the same
way once we finished discussing that not wearing the בגדי כהונה *bigdei
kehuna* invalidates, we had an opportunity to discuss how the בגדי כהונה
*bigdei kehuna* had to be worn. Now that we say not washing
your hands invalidates, we have an opportunity to discuss how you're supposed
to wash your hands. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan: כיצד מצות קידוש *Tanu
rabbanan keitzad mitzvat kiddush*? How do you wash the hands and the
feet? מניח ידו הימנית על גבי רגלו הימנית *maniach yado hayemanit al
gabei raglo hayemanit*, okay, like that, okay? And similarly, וידו השמאלית על
גבי רגלו השמאלית *veyado hasmolit al gabei raglo
hasmolit*, your—this, at the same time, like that, okay? You do your
morning exercises. I know, do your morning exercises. I got—my back hurts
just doing that. I really need to go back to the gym.
Anyway, ומקדש *u'mekadesh*, and you wash. Now I gotta tell you, like,
you know, you can't be the one that's directly operat—that's doing the
pouring, right? 'Cause you got your hands on your legs together, whatever,
you know? So, but anyway, that's where you are when
the—so, you know, when the—for the קידוש ידים *kiddush yadayim*. Let's
see, I want to see, I didn't get a chance to check.
Let me just quickly look at the רמב"ם *Rambam*
on this,
but
about how he describes how it actually would get when it came
to the pouring. מניח ידו
הימנית על גבי רגלו הימנית וידו השמאלית על גבי רגלו
השמאלית ושוחה ומקדש *maniach yado hayemanit al gabei raglo hayemanit veyado hasmolit
al gabei raglo hasmolit veshocheh u'mekadesh*. Okay,
what are you doing though? Like, are you jumping into the כיור
*kiyor*? Who's pouring it?
I don't exactly get it. I'm
not exactly getting... I mean, is
it
רגל *regel* or כף רגל *kaf regel*? What? כף רגל *kaf regel*
or רגל *regel*?
No, I mean, I assumed it meant more your feet. I have
to look into this
more. But anyway, but—but I don't really get—I don't really get this
because it's not—I mean, we when we go out to wash the
hands for the—what do you call it? We have the כהנים *kohanim*
doing it. But they really didn't have the כהנים *kohanim* doing it.
לויים *leviyim*... I mean... I'm sorry, we have the לויים *leviyim* doing
it, but they didn't have the לויים *leviyim* doing it. Maybe you
had a fellow כהן *kohen* doing it. I don't know. Did you
jump into it? Was it like a basin at the bottom? Do
they have anything in the notes that's describing it? All right, anyway,
let's keep on going. Okay. Now, אמרו לו *amru
lo*,
so now, just
says turns on one of four faucets and sanctifies both of them
simultaneously.
He turns it on while he's got his hands like that or
beforehand? I mean, it's got to be... it's like, you know, when
you go to the beach and they've got this thing, you know,
pull down or whatever. It's got to be somehow you could be
down there and have running water and somehow get under the running
water or something like that. Okay, I—but I—it would be helpful if
there was a greater description of how that exactly operated. Okay. Now.
But he does give reference to the רמב"ם *Rambam*. Which רמב"ם *Rambam*?
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* 5:16.
I was looking at 5:16. I didn't see anything there about a
running faucet. Commentary to the משנה *Mishnah*...
Yeah, all right, I'll look later. I didn't see anything there about
a running faucet. Anyway, okay. רבי Rebbi יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר מניח
שתי ידיו זו על גבי זו ושתי רגליו זו על גבי זו
ומקדש *Rebbi Yose b'rebbi Yehuda omer maniach shtei yadav zo al gabei
zo ushtei raglav zo al gabei zo u'mekadesh*. So you got your,
like, two feet on top and your two hands on top. So
rather than hand-foot hand-foot, it's, like, like this and like that. Okay,
and they said, so, אמרו לו הפלגת *amru lo hiflagta*.
They said, "You're getting a little carried away," which basically means, like,
how can a כהן *kohen* maintain stability standing, like, one foot on
top of the other? אי אפשר *ee efshar*, אי אפשר לעשות כן
*ee efshar la'asot kein*, you really can't do it. שפיר קאמרו ליה
*Shapir ka'amru lei*, that's a good response. אמר רב יוסף וחבירו מסייעו
*Amar Rav Yosef vechavero mesay'o*. No, what it means is you get
your fellow כהן *kohen* to help support you so you don't tip
over while you're standing like that. מאי בינייהו *Mai beinaihu*? What are
they debating? אמר אביי עמידה מן הצד בינייהו *Amar Abaye amida min
hatzad beinaihu*. Can you have supported standing? Is that considered halachically to
be standing? Because even when you wash your hands and feet, halachically
you can't do it sitting, you have to do it standing. אמר
ליה רב סמא בריה דרב אשי לרבינא וליתב מיתב ולקדש *Amar lei
Rav Sama brei de'Rav Ashi le'Ravina u'leyseiv meysiv u'lekadesh*? Why can't you
sit when you wash your hands? אמר קרא לשרת l'shareit. *Amar kra
leshareit*. It says לעמוד לשרת la'amod l'shareis *la'amod leshareit*. to stand to
serve, ושרות מעומד הוא, okay, I would access לעמוד לשרת l'shareit. in
another פסוק and as it says when it speaks about the washing
of the hands, it says ושרת. v'shareis. So therefore, and we know
in general that שרות sheirus service is standing, as John Milton said,
they also serve who only stand and wait. So anyway, so service
is standing and therefore since this is considered שירות, sheirut, part of
the service of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, it has to be
done standing. Interesting תוספות, Tosafot, and if you look at תוספות, Tosafot,
עמידה מן הצד כעמידה, amida min hatzad k'amida, so it
says לרבנן לא שמה עמידה מן הצד, l'rabbanan lo shemei amida min
hatzad, it's not considered really standing, ונראה כשקורין בתורה שלא לסמוך, v'ne'er
k'shekorin batorah shelo lismo'ach,
when you get an עליה aliyah don't like, you know, support yourself
on the בימה, bimah, try to stand up by yourself, משום דאמר
במגילה פרק הקורא את המגילה עומד, mishum d'amar b'Megilla perek Hakorei es
HaMegilla omeid, דבתורה בעי עמידה, d'be'torah ba'ei amida, you have to stand
when you're getting an עליה. aliyah. ובירושלמי נמי אמרינן דאסור לסמוך משום
דכשם שניתנה באימה כך נוהגים אותה באימה. u'veyirushalmi nami amrinan d'asur lismo'ach
mishum d'kesheim shenitna b'eima kach nohagim otah b'eima. The same way the
Torah was given, you have to be in a sense of awe,
be standing when you're reading the Torah or getting an עליה. aliyah.
Of course, people that are in, you know, wheelchairs or otherwise can't,
obviously, it's not מעכב, but this is more of like a לכתחילה
l'chatchilah in terms of the issues of the עליה. aliyah. Back to
the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: קידש ידיו ורגליו ביום אין צריך לקדש
בלילה. Kidesh yadav v'raglav beyom ein tzarich l'kadesh balailah. Let
when do you have to re-wash your hands? If you are doing
the night shift in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you did it
the day and now you're working into the night, just because it's
night you don't have to wash your hands again. בלילה, Balailah, if
you worked at the night and now you're going over into the
morning and continuing to do the עבודה avodah after daybreak, so צריך
לקדש ביום, tzarich l'kadesh beyom, דברי רבי. Divrei Rabbi.
Rabbi says the new day requires a new washing of hands. שהיה
רבי אומר: shehayah Rabbi omer: לינה מועלת בקידוש ידיו ורגליו. Linah mo'elet
b'kidesh yadav v'raglav. מועלת Mo'elet we normally think is a good thing.
Sleeping works for קידוש ידיו ורגליו, kidesh yadav v'raglav, but works means
works to make it required. Okay, the fact that it's been slept,
even if you didn't sleep, sleeping is the word לינה lina means
it's been the night has passed and it's now the next morning.
The passing of the night requires a new washing of hands. רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר אין לינה מועלת בקידוש ידיו ורגליו. Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Shimon omer ein lina mo'elet b'kidesh yadav v'raglav. No, it has
no impact, as long as you didn't leave the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, your original washing is still good. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we
learned another ברייתא. braita. היה עומד ומקריב אגבי מזבח כל הלילה, Hayah
omed u'makriv agabei mizbeach kol halailah, there you were, not only were
you in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you were doing עבודה, avodah,
you were putting the limbs on the sacrifice the whole night, לאורה
l'orah and then it's daybreak and you still are in the middle
of putting the limbs on the sacrifice, you gotta lot to do,
טעון קידוש ידיו ורגליו. Teun kidesh yadav v'raglav. Rabbi says the same
thing, דברי רבי. Divrei Rabbi. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר כיון שקידש
ידיו ורגליו מתחלת עבודה, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon omer keivan shekidesh yadav
v'raglav mitichilat avodah,
since you did it before you began the עבודה avodah of putting
the limbs on, אפילו מכאן ועד עשרה ימים, afilu mikan v'ad asarah
yamim, as long as you don't have like a היסח הדעת hesech
hadaas and you don't leave the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, as long
as you're sort of constantly involved in this, so אינו צריך לקדש,
eino tzarich l'kadesh, you don't have to do it again. So it
seems like it's the same debate, a slightly different scenario. צריכא, Tzericha,
you need to tell me both cases, they're slightly different. דאי אשמעינן
קמייתא, D'i ashmian kamaisa, if it had said the first one, the
first one did not describe the case that you were in the
middle of doing the עבודה avodah the whole night and going on
and continuing the עבודה avodah in the morning. So in that case,
בהא קאמר רבי, b'hi kama Rabbi, there I would say Rabbi requires
in the morning a new washing, דפסיק ליה מעבודה לעבודה, d'pasik lei
mei'avodah l'avodah, I would assume the scenario is come the morning they
put you on some different job, so even though you didn't leave
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. maybe the combination of the new day
and a new עבודה avodah requires washing the hands. אבל בהא, Aval
b'ha, here where you're still doing the עבודה avodah you were doing
at the night, it's the same process, דלא פסיק ליה, d'lo pasik
lei,
you didn't interrupt, אימא מודי ליה רבי לרבי אלעזר, eima modei lei
Rabbi l'Rabbi Elazar, maybe he would agree you don't have to do
a קידוש ידיו ורגליו. kidesh yadav v'raglav. So it tells you no,
you do, even though it was the same עבודה, avodah, the same
process, once it's daybreak you need to do it. ורבי שמעון, ואי
אשמעינן בהא, V'Rabbi Shimon, v'i ashmian b'ha, if we had just given
me that example, בהא קאמר רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, b'ha ka'amar Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon, maybe I would say because it's the same עבודה,
avodah, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon doesn't require a
new washing. אבל בהא, Aval b'ha, if there actually was a new
עבודה, avodah, wasn't the same one, a new עבודה avodah with the
new day, אימא מודי ליה לרבי, eima modei lei l'Rabbi, maybe he
would agree, צריכי, tzerichi, so you need to tell me both ways.
Rabbi says you always need to do a washing if the new
day breaks even if you're in the middle of an עבודה avodah
and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon says you never
need to do it as long as you didn't leave and there
wasn't you weren't distracted or whatever even if you shift from one
עבודה avodah to the next, the new day does not require a
new washing. Okay, now let's link it to the
פסוק. מאי טעמא דרבי, Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi, where does Rabbi get the
idea that a new day requires a new washing? דכתיב: בגישתם. d'chtiv
bigishtam, It says you know בבואם אל אהל מועד לשרת או בגישתם
אל המזבח לשרת. b'vo'am el ohel mo'ed l'shareis o b'gishtam el hamizbeach
l'shareis. When do they have to wash their hands? When they enter
into אהל מועד ohel mo'ed or when they draw close to the
מזבח. mizbeach. So what is בגישתם B'gishtam. telling you? So רש"י Rashi
I mean it a little bit begs the question, רש"י Rashi says
that the fact that it's a new day defines this even though
it's not a new ביאה, biah, it's not a new entering into
the מקדש, Mikdash, I'm still in the מקדש, Mikdash, it's a new
encounter, it's a new גישה. gisha. Now that a little bit begs
the question like who defined a new day as a new גישה.
gisha. Okay, but if רש״י Rashi says, if you look three lines
down in the wide lines, דכתיב Dichviv: בגישתם, b'gishtam וגישה דשחרית גישה
אחריתי היא, v'gisha d'shacharit gisha achrit hi, שיש כאן מערכה חדשה. sheyeish
kan maaracha chadasha. Since there's a new fire, new wood is put
on the המזבח hamizbeach and it says בגישתם אל המזבח, bigishtam el
hamizbeach, so it's seen as a new encounter of the המזבח hamizbeach
because you did something new, you refreshed the altar by putting the
new wood on it. So it's a new גישה. gisha. So רבי
Rebbi says it's a new גישה, gisha, the altar has been refreshed,
and therefore you need a new washing. מאי טעמא דרבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon דכתיב בבואם. d'chtiv b'voam. No,
because the other part of the פסוק says when you enter, and
this was not a new entry into the בית המקדש. Mikdash. ואידך,
v'idach, now רבי Rebbi, would say back, נמי הכתיב בבואם. nami hachtiv
b'voam. So he would say אי כתיב בגישתם ולא כתיב בבואם, i
ktiv bigishtam v'lo ktiv b'voam, if it only said when you encounter
and not when you enter, הוה אמינא כל גישה וגישה, hava amina
kol gisha v'gisha, I might think that every time you go back
to the המזבח hamizbeach in the same day you have to do
it a hundred times, every time you re-encounter the altar. So כתב
רחמנא בבואם. ktav Rachmana b'voam. So בבואם b'voam is telling you no,
we don't mean every time you encounter the altar, we mean in
one presence in the המקדש. Mikdash, You've entered the המקדש, you're there
for the day, you do it once. So בבואם b'voam tells you
once you've entered and you're there for the day, you don't do
it for every new encounter of the altar. בגישתם bigishtam says but
when there's something new about the altar, when it's been daybreak and
the altar is refreshed, then you do have to do it even
if you never left. That's what רבי Rebbi says. Okay, ואידך נמי
הכתיב בגישתם. v'idach nami hachtiv bigishtam. Now Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon that
says as long as you didn't leave you don't have to wash
your hands again, what does he do with the word בגישתם? bigishtam?
Just tell me בבואם, b'voam, when you come in again, if you've
been there constantly you don't have to do it. No, אי כתיב
בבואם ולא כתיב בגישתם, i ktiv b'voam v'lo ktiv bigishtam, had it
just said בבואם, b'voam, הוה אמינא אפילו ביאה ריקנית, hava amina afilu
biya reikanit, even if you entered in without the purpose of עבודה.
avoda. Any time you enter, maybe you have to do it. So
בגישתם bigishtam tells you only if you enter to do an עבודה.
avoda. הגמרא hagimara says one minute, ביאה ריקנית הכתיב לשרת, biya reikanit
hachtiv l'shareit, you can't say that, it says בבואם b'voam אל אהל
מועד el Ohel Moed לשרת. l'shareit Okay, I think it says לשרת.
l'shareit Does לשרת say בגישתם bigishtam or בבואם? b'voam? Anyway, we understand
that לשרת refers to בבואם, b'voam, so therefore I would have known
even without the word בגישתם bigishtam that it means only when you
enter to do an עבודה. avoda. אלא ella fine,
בבואם b'voam means when you enter to do an עבודה. avoda. So
what do you need בגישתם bigishtam for? For רבי, Rebbi, you need
בגישתם bigishtam to tell me that every new day you gotta do
it again. But what do you do with the בגישתם bigishtam for
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon? בגישתם מיבעי ליה לכדרב אחא בריה דרב יעקב.
bigishtam mibai lei l'che d'Rav Acha brei d'Rav Yaakov. דאמר רב אחא
בריה דרב יעקב, d'amar Rav Acha brei d'Rav Yaakov, הכל מודים בקידוש
שני כשהוא לבוש מקדש. hakol modim b'kidush sheini k'shehu lavush mikadesh. Okay,
when there's a whole debate when the כהן גדול switches בגדים, bgadim,
when do you wash your hands? Before you take off the old
בגדים bgadim or after you take off the old בגדים? bgadim? Okay,
but that's a debate. Then you go to the מקוה, mikva, then
you put on the בגדים, bgadim, and here we're saying that whatever
the debate was about when you took off the old ones, everybody
agrees that when you put on the new בגדים, bgadim, you first
put on the new בגדים bgadim and then you wash your hands.
You don't wash your hands before the new בגדים. bgadim. Why does
everybody agree first the new בגדים bgadim and then wash your
hands? דאמר קרא או בגישתם, d'amar kra o bigishtam, מי שאינו מחוסר
אלא גישה בלבד, יצא זה שמחוסר לבישה וגישה. mi sheino mechusar ella
gisha bilvad, yatza ze shemechusar levisha v'gisha. Because the washing of the
hands has to be juxtaposed with בגישתם, bigishtam, with entering in and
beginning the עבודה. avoda. And if you washed your hands before you
put on the בגדים, bgadim, it would not be the washing right
before you encountered because you'd have to then put on the בגדים.
bgadim. So you have to have the בגדים bgadim on, be ready,
and the only thing that's preventing you is the washing of your
hands, you wash your hands and now בגישתם. bigishtam. Okay, so what
do you have? בבואם b'voam tells you everybody agrees
that once you enter and you're present you don't have to do
it multiple times. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon says that's all that tells
me is until you leave you never have to wash your hands
again. רבי says no, בגישתם bigishtam tells me if it's considered a
new encounter because it's a new day, then even without leaving you
have to wash your hands. And Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon says what
I learn from בגישתם bigishtam is this הלכה halacha that you wash
your hands after putting on the בגדים, bgadim, that it comes right
before you encounter. I do not learn what you, רבי, say, that
a new day requires a new washing. I say as long as
you're present and haven't left, you don't have to wash your hands
again. Okay, interesting debate, let's say somebody's up all night learning, do
they have to wash their hands in the morning and make a—
or whatever they're up all night, you know, it's an interesting similar
debate הלכה למעשה, halacha l'ma'aseh, it's debated in the פוסקים, poskim, do
you have to wash your hands first thing in the morning if
you've been up all night? Okay, so sort of interesting type of
a parallel question.